Guide to the Cooper Bridge Plan collection, 1887-1889 (bulk)
Cooper Bridge collection, 1887-1889 (bulk)
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Cooper bridge collection, 1887-1889 (bulk)
4709
Theodore, Cooper 1839-1919
.9 cubic ft. plus 278 items.
Technical drawings, bluprints, correspondence
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Consists mainly of letters (194 items) and drawings (ca. 150) sent to Theodore Cooper, giving him information for the important paper on American railroad bridges which he published in Transactions of the American Society of Civil Engineers in 1889. Also contains notes, sketches, and a few photographs.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
American civil engineer (1839-1919). Author of the first authoritative specifications on bridge construction, published in 1884.
Theodore Cooper: A Biographical Outline
1839 Born January 13th in Cooper's Plain, NY, the son of John Cooper, Jr., a physician, and Elizabeth M. Evans.
1858 graduated as civil engineer from the Resselaer Institute (now Rensselaer Polytechnic) at the age of nineteen
1861 Becomes Assistant Engineer on the Troy and Greenfield Railroad and Hoosac Tunnel. The same year enlists in the Navy and becomes Assistant Engineer for the construction of the gunboat Chocura, on which he will serve for the last three years of the Civil War.
1865 Detached from the Chocura, he is ordered to the United States Naval Academy at Newport, RI, then to Annapolis, Md., as Instructor in the new department of Steam Engineering.
1868 Ordered to the Nyack in the South Pacific, where he will serve for two years.
1870 Returns to the Naval Academy.
1872 Resignes from the Navy. In May Capt. James B. Eads, Engineer of the Bridge and Tunnel Company, appoints Cooper the inspector of steel manufacturing for the St. Louis Bridge. He also appoints him superintendent of Andrew Carnegie's giant Keystone Bridge Company in Pittsburgh. At a later point Eads puts Cooper in charge of the construction of the St. Louis Bridge, a successful project that will launch Cooper's career as a bridge engineer.
1879 Sets up as independent consulting engineer in New York. Among his most prestigious projects will be the Seekonk Bridge in Providence, the Sixth Bridge in Pittsburgh, the Second Avenue Bridge in New York City, the Newburyport Bridge over the Merrimac River, and the Junction Bridges over the Allegheny River. His paper "The Use of Steel for Bridges" is published in the Transactions of the American Society of Civil Engineers. Cooper will receive a Normal Medal for this work.
1884 Contributes the important work "General Specifications for Iron Railroad Bridges and Viaducts," the first authoritative specifications on bridge construction ever published and circulated.
1885/1885 Serves as director of the American Society of Civil Engineers.
1889 His paper "American Railroad Bridges" is published in the Transactions of the American Society of Civil Engineers. Cooper will receive a Normal Medal for this work.
1894 Appointed by the late President Cleveland as a member of a board of five engineers to determine the span of the Hudson River Bridge. Other consulting work will include the New York Public Library, the Suburban Rapid Transit Company, the New York Rapid Transit Commission, the Boston Rapid Transit Commission, and the harlem River Commission.
1897 Accepts to serve as consulting engineer for the construction of the Quebec Bridge by the Quebec Bridge Company.
1907 The Quebec Bridge collapses, effectively ending Cooper's career as a bridge engineer.
1919 Dies on August 24th in New York City.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Consists mainly of letters (194 items) and drawings (ca. 150) sent to Theodore Cooper, giving him information for the important paper on American railroad bridges which he published in Transactions of the American Society of Civil Engineers in 1889. Also contains notes, sketches, and a few photographs. Drawings are mainly prints and blueprints of railroad bridges, including ones designed by Theodore Burr, Timothy Palmer, Lewis Wernwag, and Albert H. Fink. Correspondents include the American Society of Civil Engineers; D.M. Stauffer, editor of Engineering News magazine; H. Bissell, chief engineer, Boston and Maine Rail Road; A.J. Swift, chief engineer, Delaware & Hudson Canal Company; Palmer C. Ricketts, director of Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, and T.R. Lawson, his assistant; Henry McCormick Jr., president of Harrisburg Bridge Company; and the Lehigh Valley Rail Road Company. The collection includes several items about the work of Theodore Burr and Timothy Palmer, earlier civil engineers who had each designed a number of railroad bridges.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Cooper, Theodore,1839-1919; Bissell, H.; Burr, Theodore.; Fink, Albert, 1827-1897.; Lawson, T. R.; McCormick, Henry,; Palmer, Timothy.; Ricketts, Palmer C.; Stauffer, D. M.; Swift, A. J.; Wernwag, Lewis.; American Society of Civil Engineers.; Lehigh Valley Railroad.
Subjects:
Bridges--United States.; Railroad bridges--United States.; Railroads--United States.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Digital Reproductions for Series I. Correspondence, Incoming. Box 1 Folder 1 are available online at: http://rmc.library.cornell.edu/cgi-bin/cooper/docviewer?did=cooper0101
RELATED MATERIALS
Collecting program: History of Science Collection.
ARRANGEMENT DESCRIPTION
For Series III, entries appear in alphabetical order by working title. Original titles, whether or not they are the same as the working title, appear in quotation marks, following the working title. Original titles include both those that actually appear on the piece itself, and those that, at some point in the collection's history, had been noted on the verso of some untitled pieces. Working titles were determined according to the following criteria:
1. Proper name of bridge, if that is either the same as, or appears in, the original title of the item, e.g., Blue River Bridge for "General Plan of Blue River Bridge"; also, if the proper name is known, even if it is not explicit on the item
2. Proper name of bridge *type* (or of eponymous individual) if that is either the same as, or appears in, the original title, or is known, e.g., Pratt truss bridge for "Plan of draw, Newburyport ..."; Fink triangular truss bridges … for "Bridges on the B. & O. ... by Albert Fink"
3. Name of town or of waterway; e.g., Easton bridge for "Highway bridge...at Easton, Pa."; Jones' Falls bridge for "N. C. Ry. Bridge over Jones' Falls"
4. Name of railroad, if that is the most prominent or the only proper name in the original, e.g., New York Central & Hudson River RR...Bridge for "N.Y.C. & H.R.R.R. ... Bridge #307"
5. Bridge type or bridge part, in absence of any proper names
Entries that are part of composite items (more than one bridge per plan) are indicated as such. Dimensions of each item are in approximate inches.
Note: Graphics that appear in Theodore Cooper's paper, *American Railroad Bridges* (Transactions of the American Society of Civil Engineers, 1889) are indicated by: [ARB Pl. number]
SERIES LIST
Series I. Correspondence
Box 1
Series II. Additional papers
Box 1
Series III. Drawings, Prints, Blueprints
Boxes 2-4, mapcase
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Correspondence
  - Incoming Correspondence:
    - Digital files of items from Box 1 Folder 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Digital Reproductions for Series I. Correspondence, Incoming. Box 1 Folder 1 are available online at: http://rmc.library.cornell.edu/cgi-bin/cooper/docviewer?did=cooper0101
    - [unidentified] (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers (J. Becker, John Bogart) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Boston & Maine RR (H. Bissell, Chief Engineer) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bouscaren, G., Consulting Engineer (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Buffalo, NY, City Engineer Office (Edward B. Guthrie) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Central Railroad & Banking Co. of Ga., Savannah, GA (D. W. Bowman) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Chicago, Milwaukee & St. Paul Railway Co. (D.J. Whittemore, Chief Engineer; Onward Bates) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Cincinnati, New Orleans & Texas Pacific Railway Co. (Ward Baldwin, Assistant Engineer) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Delaware & Hudson Canal Company (A.J. Swift, Chief Engineer) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Engineering News (D. McN. Stouffer, Editor) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Florence iron River Company (Manfred A. Hauschild, Chief Engineer) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Hutton, William R. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Iron city Bridge Works (Albert Schultz) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Keefer, Theod.? C. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Kellogg, Chas. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Lafayette College, Department of Civil Engineering (J.G. Fox?) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Lehigh Valley Rail Road Co. (Rob H. Sayer, vice President) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Linville, J.H. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Louisville Bridge and Iron Company (J.M. Johnson, Engineer) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Louisville & Nashville Railroad Company (Hantfort?, Chief Engineer) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - McCormick, Henry (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Michaelis?, O.E. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Michigan Central Railway Co. (J.D. Hawks, Chief Engineer) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Missouri Pacific Railway Co. (R.M. Peck, Supt.) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - New Jersey Steel & Iron Co. (C.E. Hewitt) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - New York, Lake Erie & Western Railroad Co. (C.W. Buckley?, Engineer) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - New York, State of. Office of State Engineer and Surveyor (Arthur S.C. Wurtele?, Deputy State Eng. & Sur. John Bogart, State Engineer and Surveyor) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Pencoyd Iron Works (Percival Roberts) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Company (W.H. Bron, Chief Engineer) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Pennsylvania, University of. Course of Civil Engineering (L.M. Haupt Philadelphia Department of Public Works (Samuel L. Smedley, Chief Engineer and Surveyor) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute (Palmer C. Ricketts); includes five photos of wooden models of Waterford & Lansingburgh Bridge (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Rochester Bridge & Iron Works (Alfred M. Moss, Asst. Engineer) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Schenectady, City of. (part of letter with description of bridge) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Shunk, William Findlay (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Stephen Tilton & Co. (George Tilton) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - St. Louis & San Francisco Railway Company (James Dun, Chf. Eng.) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Thaner School of civil Engineer (Robert Fletcher) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Thomson, G.H. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Trowbridge, W.P. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Union Bridge Company (Thos. J. Long) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Union Pacific Railway Company (V.G. Bogue, Chief engineer) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - United States Military Academy at West Point. Library (Edward S. Holden, Librarian) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Vose, Geo. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Wabash Western Railroad Company (W.C. Lincoln?, Cheif Engineer) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Watson, Robert M. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Worthen, Wm. E. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Outgoing Correspondence
    - Chicago, Milwaukee & St. Paul Railway Co. (Onward Bates, Office of Engr. and Supt't, Bridges and Buildings) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence among others
    - H. Bissell to Albert Cumier (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II. Additional papers
  - Notes (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Reports (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series III. Drawings, Prints, Blueprints
  - Barren River bridge, Louisville & Nashville RR, Undated (Folder 12)
    See: Fink triangular truss bridges
  - Blue River Bridge, 1858; 17.5 x 11.5; Photolithograph on thin paper (Folder 17)
    General Plan of Blue River Bridge. J.M. & I.R.R Jeffersonville, Madison, & Indianapolis R.R. [ARB Pl. XIX]
  - Bollman Patent Iron Suspension Truss Bridge, 1871-03-17; 19.5 x 13.5; 4 copies; Lithograph on thin paper (Folder 14)
    Bollman Patent Iron Suspension Truss Bridge Built by Wendell Bollman, Patapsco Bridge & Iron Works Established 1858 at Canton Office: No. 8 South Gay St. Baltimore [ARB Pl. XII]
  - Bollman Patent Iron Suspension Truss Bridge, Undated; 39 x 24; Print (Folder 62)
    Elevation of truss; cross-section; plan of floor bracing; plan of top bracing; intermediate post; pedestal
  - Brandywine Creek Bridge, New York & Erie RR, 1848 (Whipple), 1848; 37.5 x 30.5; Print (Folder 60)
    Brandywine Creek Bridge, N.Y. & E.R.R., Susquehanna Div. Sec. 199. Designed and built by Squire Whipple C E 1848. Scale one inch to three feet.
  - Bridge parts: channels and ends of posts, Undated; 37.5 x 17.5 (Folder 37)
    Untitled drawing in red and black, labelled: " 10" channels, 93 lbs. pr. yd."
  - Bridge parts: counter rod, Undated; 38 x 25; Print on vellum (Folder 46)
    Intermediate post, pedestal, suspension bars (2), upper chord panel
  - Bridge parts: joints, Undated; 13 x 10 (Folder 1)
    Untitled drawing of metal (?) joints
  - Bridge parts: shoes, washers, posts, Undated; 24.5 x 18 (Folder 18)
    Untitled diagrams of shoes, washers, and posts (side and top views)
  - Bridge parts: trusses, 1861-04-13; 17.5 x 14 (Folder 3)
    18 untitled diagrams of trusses, including details of joints, etc.
  - Bridge specifications, force diagram, 1887-12-06; 37.5 x 24 (Folder 47)
    Alternative of Class B, Cooper's specifications.
  - Bridge specifications: truss, Undated; 22.5 x 31 (Folder 44)
    Untitled table of measurements for parts of truss (T.C., M.B., C.B., Post, and B.C.; i.e., chords, bars, and posts?) with 16 joints, with corresponding diagram of truss
  - Bridge type: drawbridge, Undated; 23 x 12; Blueprint (Folder 4)
    Untitled blueprint diagram of a drawbridge, side elevation
  - Bridge type: suspension, Undated; 27 x 18 (Folder 25)
    Untitled color drawing of tubular (?) suspension (?) bridge
  - Cascade Glen Arch, New York & Erie RR, 1848; 31.5 x 30.5; 23 x 30.5; Print in two consecutive pieces (Folder 59 a,b)
    Cascade-Glen Arch. 275 ft. Span. Delaware Division N.Y. & E.R.R., 1848. Designed by Julius W. Adams Resident Engineer (1893 Past President & Honorary Member Am. Soc. C.E.)
  - Chemung River bridge, 1872-04-02; 40 x 23; 2 copies; Print (Folder 30)
    Wrought iron railroad bridge over the Chemung River at Elmira, N.Y. Erie Railway.
  - Columbia Bridge over Schuylkill River, Salmon River Bridge, 1832; 36 x 31 (Folder 61)
    Columbia Bridge across the Schuylkill River near Peters' Island. Philadelphia & Columbia Railroad.
  - Cumberland River Bridge, Louisville & Nashville RR, Undated; 22.5 x 17.5; Lithograph on tracing (?) paper (Folder 19)
    Cumberland River Bridge L. & N. R. R. Nashville Tenn.
  - David Lyman Viaduct--details, etc., 1869; 24 x 31 (Folder 64 a,b)
    David Lyman Viaduct, New Haven, Middletown and Willimantic RR 1869" [from verso]: "Details of Connections for Combination Viaduct. Built November 1869 By Clarke, Reeves & Co., Now: The Phoenix Bridge Co. Phoenixville, Pa.
  - David Lyman Viaduct--general plan, 1869; 40.5 x 31; 24 x 25.5; 24 x 31; Print in three consecutive pieces (Folder 63 a,b,c)
    General Plan David Lyman Viaduct, New Haven, Middletown & Willimantic RR Built by The Phoenix Bridge Co. Phoenixville Pa. 1869. General elevation, Horizontal section at AB.. Middle piece also includes "Top view.
  - Dunkirk, Allegheny Valley & Pittsburgh R.R. Bridge, 1892-03-21; 30.5 x 29; 17.5 x 28.5; Print in two pieces (Folder 66 a,b)
    Dunkirk, Allegheny Valley & Pittsburgh R.R. Bridge at Youngsville, Pa.
  - Easton Bridge and Schuylkill Permanent Bridge, Undated; 27.5 x 12.5; Drawing (Folder 28)
    Highway bridge over the river Delaware at Easton, Pa. [ARB Pl. V]
  - Easton Bridge elevation and side view, Undated; 40.5 x 13.5; Drawing (Folder 35)
    Highway bridge over the river Delaware at Easton, Pa.
  - Economy bridge, Wernwag's Bridges, Undated; With four other bridges on lithograph (Folder 9)
    Bridge ‘Economy,’ The Principle of which is across Neshaminy, on the Post Road from Philada. to N. York & over Frankfort Creek
  - Elizabeth River bridge, Fink bridges on the Norfolk & Petersburg RR, 1860; 25.5 x 19.5; Print (Folder 10)
    Bridges on the Norfolk and Petersburg Rail Road. Bridge over South Branch of Elizabeth River (Fig. 14). Bridge at Petersburg, Va. (Fig. 16). Bridge at Norfolk, Va. (Fig. 18.)
  - Fink combination bridge [composite], Undated; 40 x 27; 4 copies; Print (Folder 48)
    5 individual plans (plus details) on single sheet, Whipple Trapezoidal Truss; Plan of Green River Bridge; 400 feet span of Ohio River Br. at Louisville; General Plan of Blue River Bridge [ARB Pl. XIV]
  - Fink triangular truss bridges, Baltimore & Ohio, 1860; 25.5 x 19.5; Print (Folder 13)
    Bridges on the Baltimore and Ohio, and North Western Virginia Rail Road; on the Plan Patented by Albert Fink.
  - Fink triangular truss bridges, N. W. Virginia, 1860; 25 x 19.5; Print (Folder 12)
    Bridges on the North Western Va. and Louisville and Nashville R.R. on the plan patented by Albert Fink
  - Fink triangular truss: details, Undated; 38 x 25.5; Print (Folder 29)
    Details of Fink Triangular truss
  - Goelzsch-Thal Viaduct, Saxony, Kinzua Viaduct; Pecos River Viaduct, 1900; 22 x 20; Blueprint (Folder 20)
    Over the Valley of the Goelzsch Creek, Saxony. Saxo-Bavarian R.R.. Time of construction: 6 years; extreme height: 260 feet length over all: 1900 feet; cost: 7,000,000 Marks [$1,680,000]
  - Green River Bridge, Fink bridges on the Norfolk & Petersburg Rail Road, Undated (Folder 10)
    Plan of Green River Bridge Louisville & Nashville Rail Road, full side view [part of ARB Pl. XV]
  - Gwynn's Falls Bridge: chord details, Undated; 38 x 24.5 (Folder 31 a)
    Chord Details of Gwynn's Falls Bridge on Washn Line B. & P. R. R. Long Span
  - Gwynn's Falls Bridge: compression members A-C, Undated; 38.5 x 24 (Folder 31 b)
    Details of Compression Memb'rs Gwynn's Falls Bridge on Washn Line B. & P. R. R
  - Gwynn's Falls Bridge: compression members D-G, Undated; 37 x 24.5 (Folder 31 c)
  - Gwynn's Falls Bridge: floorsystem, Undated; 37.5 x 25.5 (Folder 31 d)
    Details of Floorsystem Gwynn's Falls Bridge on Washn Line B. & P. R. R
  - Gwynn's Falls Bridge: intersections, Undated; 38.5 x 25 (Folder 31 e)
    Details of Intersections Gwynn's Falls Bridge on Washn Line B. & P. R. R. Long Span
  - Gwynn's Fall Bridge: struts, Undated; 38 x 24.5 (Folder 31 f)
    Diagram and Details of Struts. Gwynn's Falls Bridge on Washn Line B. & P. R. R
  - Harpers Ferry Bridge (timber), 1836; 24 x26; 41.5 x 30.5 (Folder 82)
    Harper's Ferry Bridge B. & O. R.R.. Designed by B. H. Latrobe. Built by Lewis Wernwag, General plan [crosses both Potomac R. and Chesapeake & Ohio Canal]; elevation of truss; cross-sections; plans; other details
  - Harpers Ferry Bridge (iron), 1852; 17 x 26 (Folder 65)
    Winchester Span. Baltimore and Ohio Railroad. Designed by Wendel Bollman
  - Howe truss bridge, 1840; 26 x 13.5; Drawing on vellum (Folder 33)
    [ARB Pl. XI]
  - Howe truss bridge, iron, 1849; 37.5 x 30; Print (Folder 72)
    Iron Howe Truss Bridge. Boston & Providence R.R.. Built by Stone & Harris, Springfield, Mass.
  - Howe truss bridge, modern type, 1890; 40.5 x 30.5; Print (Folder 73)
    Modern Type Arched Howe Truss. Wilson Brothers & Co. Engineers, Philadelphia
  - Howe truss bridge, 2d form, Salisbury, Ct., 1870; 37 x 30.5; Print (Folder 74)
    Howe Truss Bridge at Salisbury, Conn. Built in 1870. By R.F. Hawkins. 130 ft. span. Presented by R.F. Hawkins' Iron Works. Springfield, Mass. Successors to Wm. Howe, Stone & Harris and Harris & Hawkins
  - Howe truss bridge (first Howe railroad bridge), Springfield, Mass., 1838; 38.5 x 30.5; Print (Folder 71)
    Howe Truss Bridge over the Connecticut River, Springfield, Mass. Built about 1838 by Wm. Howe. Presented by R.F. Hawkins' Iron Works Springfield, Mass. Successors to Wm. Howe, Stone & Harris and Harris & Hawkins
  - Howe truss bridge (first Howe railroad bridge), Springfield, Mass., 1838; 34 x 30.5; Blueprint (Folder 70)
    7 views: elevation; cross-section; details of bottom chord; longitudinal section; plan showing bottom chord; details of top chord; top plan. Lower rt.: "Pontrichet's improved sunprint"
  - Hudson River Tunnel, 1881; 17.5 x 19; Print (Folder 21)
    Longitudinal and cross section, showing new method of employing a caisson and completing the walls; also, method of driving pilot tunnel and removing the silt.
  - Jones' Falls bridge, Undated; 41 x 24.5; Print (Folder 51)
    Northern Central RR "N. C. Ry. Bridge over Jones' Falls, Details of Diagram
  - Jordan Creek Viaduct (cast iron), 1856; 20.5 x 31.5; 39.5 x 31.5; 22 x 31; 15.5 x 31; 29 x 31.5; Print in five pieces (Folder 102 a,b,c,d)
    General Plan of the Jordan Creek Viaduct, for the Catasauqua & Fogelsville R.R. Designed constructed & erected by F.C. Lowthorp. Built 1856 Rebuilt 1889
  - Jordan Creek Viaduct, 1889 (Chapman), 1889; 40.5 x 28; 37 x 31; Print In two consecutive pieces; entire longitudinal view (Folder 101 a,b,c)
    C. W. Chapman, spt. Engr. Designed, constructed & erected by Edge Moor Bridge Works, Edge Moor, Del.
  - Jordan Creek Viaduct, duplicate, 1889 (Box 3)
    Includes cross-section and additional details; very long, rolled
  - Jordan Creek Viaduct, 1893; 40.5 x 28; Print (Folder 100)
    Two longitudinal views: top: "built 1856;" bottom: "built 1889;" noted at lower right corner: Wm. C. Bolgiano 1893;" stamped: "Pontrichet's improved sunprint
  - Kentucky River Bridge, 1877; 24.5 x 30.5; 25.5 x 30.5; Print in two pieces (Folder 80 a,b)
    Kentucky River Bridge. Cincinnati & Southern Railway. Designed and built by C. Shaler Smith
  - Keystone Bridge Company (bridge details only), 1868; 42 x 28; Print (Folder 54)
    The Keystone Bridge Company of Pittsburgh, Pa., manufacturers of Linville and Piper patent wrought iron bridges. Patented Jan. 14th 1862 and Oct. 31st 1865. Especially adapted to Rail Road Traffic for spans of 100 to 400 feet
  - Kinzua Viaduct, Undated; 22 x 20; Blueprint (Folder 20)
    Kinzua Viaduct, Penn'a. N.Y.L.E. & West. Coal & R.R. Co.
  - Kinzua Viaduct: details of connections, 1893; 31 x 40; Print (Folder 93)
    Kinzua Viaduct Details of Connections. Design. and built by the Phenix [sic] Bridge Comp. Phoenixville, Pa.
  - Kinzua Viaduct: general elevation, 1882; 31 x 41; 31 x 40; Print in two consecutive pieces (Folder 94 a,b)
    General Plan Kinzua Viaduct N.Y.L.E. & W.RR. designed & built by the Phoenix Bridge Co. Phoenixville, Pa.
  - Kinzua Viaduct: general elevation, duplicate, 1882; Blueprint (Box 4)
  - Lancaster-Schuylkill Bridge, Undated (Folder 5)
    Lancaster-Schuylkill Bridge Over the River at Philadelphia. Single arch. Invented by Lewis Wernwag - Executed by him & Joseph Johnson. General Finish by R. Mills Esq
  - Lehigh Coal and Navigation Company, 1883-10-29; 36 x 20; Print (Folder 43)
    Lehigh Coal and Navigation Cos. Rail Road Bridge at Turn hole. Broken April 1868
  - Lilandsosen bridge, Norway, Undated; 28 x 8.5; Blueprint (Folder 32)
    Bro over Lilandsosen vel Bulken
  - Little Juniata, cast iron arch bridge, 1864; 39.5 x 30.5; Print (Folder 83)
    Little Juniata Bridge, No. 8, Pensylvania [sic] Railroad. Designed by J.H. Linville
  - Long's Truss bridge, 1st form, 1833; 36.5 x 30.5; Print (Folder 67)
    Long's Truss Bridge, 1833 double track; 6 separate views: side view of truss; plan (?) of truss; x-sect.; post; main brace; counter brace
  - Long's Truss bridge, 2nd form, 1837; 37.5 x 30.5; Pen & ink drawing on vellum (Folder 39)
    Single track, “2d form”; untitled, but 6 views correspond to those of "1833" above
  - Long's Truss bridge, 2nd form, 1837; 35.5 x 24; Print (Folder 39)
  - Long's Truss bridge, 2nd form, 1837; 35.5 x 24; Print (Folder 75)
    Duplicate of Other Long's Truss bridge, 2nd form
  - Lowthorp Truss bridge, Lanesboro, Pa., 1860; 40.5 x 30.5; Print (Folder 68)
    Lowthorp Truss Bridge. Designed and patented by F.C. Lowthorp Trenton, N.J [ARB Pl. XXV]